Finding Aid for the Léon R. Yankwich Papers LSC.0538
UCLA Library Special Collections
Léon R. Yankwich papers
1909-1959
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yankwich, Léon R. (Léon René), b. 1888
LSC.0538
103 Linear Feet (206 boxes and 26 oversize boxes)
Léon René Yankwich (1888-1975) was a judge in the Los Angeles County Superior Court (1927-35) and in the U.S. District Court of the Southern District of California (1935-64). He presided over one of the first cases under the Smith Act, as well as cases involving the ownership of the Elk Hills oil fields, and the Hollywood 10. He also contributed many articles to law reviews and published books. The collection consists of Yankwich's correspondence, manuscripts of speeches, photographs, memorabilia, legal papers, books, and other printed material including manuscripts for his books It's libel or contempt if you print it and The nature of our freedom.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Léon R. Yankwich, 1959.
Gift of Peter E. Yankwich, 1975.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942340423606533
Biography
Léon René Yankwich was born on September 25, 1888 in Jassy, Roumania; LLB, Williamette University in 1909; JD (1926), LLD (1929), Loyola University (Los Angeles); came to the U.S. in 1907; admitted to California and Oregon bar, 1909; practiced law in Modesto, California (1909-16) and Los Angeles (1916-27); judge, Los Angeles County Superior Court, 1927-35; judge, U.S. District Court of the Southern District of California, 1935-64; presided over one of the first cases under the Smith Act, as well as cases involving the ownership of the Elk Hills oil fields, and the Hollywood 10; contributed many articles to law reviews; published books include It's libel or contempt if you print it (1950) and The nature of our freedom (1950); he died on February 9, 1975.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts of speeches, photographs, memorabilia, legal papers, books, and other printed material by Léon R. Yankwich, pertaining to his career as a lawyer, judge, and author. Includes transcripts of trials, legal briefs, articles, drafts of books, newspaper clippings, and other printed materials relating to copyright law and other legal subjects. Includes manuscripts for his books It's libel or contempt if you print it and The nature of our freedom.
Expanded Scope and Content
This register lists contents of Judge Leon Yankwich's papers as packed by him for the Library. It is a temporary means of locating material that may be called for. The collection will have to be sorted and arranged.
JVM (August 6, 1959)
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Material regarding Yankwich's federal judgeship appointment.
Los Angeles Superior Court correspondence files.
U.S. District Court correspondence files.
Addenda.
Addenda no.2.
Clippings, election precinct results, and memorabilia.
Items Removed from Collection
Tomorrow: February (2 copies), March, June-July 1924; February 1925. Housed in Southern California Serials (Collection 1601 T598 Box 147). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Sports & Vanities: November, December (2 copies) 1926; January, February (2 copies), March (2 copies), May, November 1927. Housed in Southern California Serials (Collection 1601 S764v Box 147). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Judges -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Yankwich, Léon R. (Léon René), b. 1888
- Material re Yankwich's Federal Judgeship Appointment, 1935
  - Copies of endorsements. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Envelope containing letters re the appointment. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters of recommendation. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copies of inauguration ceremonies. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Folders marked: Congrats. and numbered: I-V., (5 folders) (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents note
    Letters of congratulation on his appointment.
  - Newspaper and magazine articles re his appointment., (3 folders) (Box 3)
    Also, legal papers.
  - Papers re the Melvin Butterbaugh Estate. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript notes and sketches of his addresses, 1933-1934. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Copies of law examinations given at Loyola University, Los Angeles, by Judge Yankwich. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Marked: Crime and Criminals, and containing chiefly newspaper and magazine articles on this subject. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings re cases decided by Judge Yankwich in Portland, Oregon. (Box 6, Envelope 1)
  - Newspaper clippings re cases decided by Judge Yankwich in Tacoma, Washington. (Box 6, Envelope 2)
  - Copies of letters of recommendation for appointment to the 9th Circuit Court of Appeals vacancy, 1943. (Box 6, Envelope 3)
  - The United States vs. Arthur L. Bell, Transcript of Trial and opinion and indictment, [21 vol., typescript] (Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10)
    - vol.1-5. (Box 7)
    - vol.7-11. (Box 8)
    - vol.12-16. (Box 9)
    - vol.17-21. (Box 10)
  - The United States vs. San Francisco Electrical Contractors Association, Transcript of trial., August 30, 1944.; (9 vol. [Typescripts]) (Box 11)
  - Transcripts of trials re World War II Selective Service Act violations., [Typescripts] (Box 12)
  - It's libel or contempt if you print it.. (book) by Judge Yankwich (Box 13-14, 230-231)
    General note
    See Addenda, Box 120.
    - Typescript draft., (2 copies) (Box 13)
    - Galley proof. (Box 14)
      Includes rough draft, notes and typescript draft for second edition.
    - Correspondence, contracts and reviews. (Box 230)
    - Reviews. (Box 231)
      Also, some reviews of his The nature of our freedom.
- Los Angeles Superior Court Correspondence Files, 1927-1935
  (Arranged Alphabetically)
  - A - C. (Box 15)
  - D - J. (Box 16)
  - K - O. (Box 17)
  - P - S. (Box 18)
  - T - Z. (Box 19)
- U.S. District Court Correspondence Files, 1935-1949
  - A - C. (Box 20)
  - D - G. (Box 21)
  - H - K. (Box 22)
  - L - M. (Box 23)
  - N - Q. (Box 24)
  - R - S. (Box 25)
  - T - Z. (Box 26)
- Memos, local rules from various judges for period covered by correspondence, 1935-1949. (Box 27)
- Material re Los Angeles Superior Court Judgeship Campaign, 1934. (Box 28)
  Includes campaign letters, letters of endorsement and congratulation.
  See Addenda, Box 123.
- Correspondence re his candidacy for appointment to a vacancy in the 9th District Court of Appeals, 1934.; (2 folders) (Box 29)
- Material concerning his appearance before the Senator Jack Teny Un-American Activities Investigation Committee, 1948. (Box 29)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, and a file of Yankwich's publications.
- [Miscellaneous Material]
  In alphabetical order.
  - A - B. (Box 30)
  - C - L. (Box 31)
  - M. (Box 32)
  - N - R. (Box 33)
  - S. (Box 34)
  - T - Z. (Box 35)
- Material re attack on Yankwich by Congressman Richard Vail, March 27, 1952. (Box 36)
- Material re Lester Cole referred to in the Vail attack. Note books, manuscripts of articles, lectures, etc. (Box 36)
- Copies of printed articles and books. (Box 37-54, 56-59)
- Lectures. (Box 60, Box 61, Box 62, Box 63)
- Uncorrected galley proofs of his The nature of our freedom. (Box 55)
- Material re early cases in Los Angeles. (Box 64, Box 65, Box 66, Box 67)
- Literary articles. (Box 68)
- [Miscellaneous Materials]
  - A. (Box 69)
  - B. (Box 70)
  - C - D. (Box 71)
  - F - People vs. Follett. (Box 72)
  - F - G. (Box 73)
  - H. (Box 74)
  - I - J. (Box 75)
  - K. (Box 76)
  - L - M (remainder of alphabet lacking). (Box 77)
    [For M- R, see Boxes 125-128]
  - A - M. (Box 78)
  - N - Z. (Box 79)
  - S. (Box 81, Box 82, Box 83)
  - T (incomplete file). (Box 84)
  - U - Z. (Box 85)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 80, 86)
- Papers relating to Modesto cases. (Box 80)
- Miscellaneous legal papers. (Box 86)
- Escobar papers. (Box 87)
- Earl vs. Examiner et al. (Box 87)
- State of Washington vs. Angevine. (Box 87)
- Snivley vs. Los Angeles Record. (Box 88)
- Earl vs. Examiner (briefs on appeal). (Box 88)
- In the matter of the Press Association. (Box 88)
- Snivley vs. the Record (pleadings). (Box 89)
- Alien land law and other opinions. (Box 89)
- Crawford vs. Hawe. (Box 90)
- Early Los Angeles activities, Bar Association Business. (Box 91)
- Typed originals of eight hour law briefs. (Box 91)
- Lectures, 1919, 1920. (Box 91)
- Modesto War Activities, 1914-1916. (Box 91)
- Press Association briefs. (Box 92)
- Snivley appeal briefs. (Box 92)
- Libel notes. (Box 92)
- Brief and record in first Oregon case. (Box 92)
- Deaman brief in eight hour law case. (Box 92)
- Yankwich personal libel briefs. (Box 93)
- Modesto War Activities. (Box 94)
- Escobar vs. Rogers, etc. (Box 95)
- Radio Addresses. (Box 95)
- Series 1-3. (Box 96)
- Series 4-5 (Box 97)
- Opinions. (Box 97)
- 1927-1931. (Box 98)
- April-September 1931. (Box 99)
- October-December 1931. (Box 100)
- 1932-1934. (Box 101)
- 1934-1935. (Box 102)
- 1935-1937. (Box 103)
- 1937-1939. (Box 104)
- 1949-1951. (Box 105)
- U.S. District Court Opinions., 1935-1949.; (4 vol.) (Box 106)
- Appelate Court Decisions (Department of Los Angeles Superior Court)., (1 vol.) (Box 106)
- Circuit Court of Appeals., (1 vol.) (Box 106)
- Printed briefs, pleas, etc. of important cases, chiefly California. (Box 107, Box 108, Box 109, Box 110, Box 111, Box 112)
  Includes typescripts.
- Proceedings of the California Bar Association, 1917, 1920, 1924. (Box 112)
- Libel case clippings. (Box 113)
- Material on California State Supreme Court Recommendations, January 1958. (Box 113)
- Personal items, including personal letters to, July 15, 1925. (Box 114)
- Notes on bankruptcy. (Box 114)
- Espionage case. (Box 115)
- Materials re the following cases: U.S. vs. Graham (refugee case); U.S. vs. Smith; and U.S. vs. Hunt. (Box 115)
- New stories, 1941. (Box 116)
- Personal items, 1934. (Box 116)
- Judicial questions [legal]. (Box 116)
- Drummond spy trial. (Box 117)
- Report of Special Committee to investigate bankruptcy and receivership proceedings and administration of justice in U.S. Courts. 74th Congress, 2nd session. (Box 117)
- Rupert Trumbull referee in bankruptcy materials. (Box 117)
- Material on appointment to judgeship. (Box 117)
- Briefs on women's eight hour law. (Box 118)
- First brief in Oregon after passing bar examination. (Box 118)
- Essay in long hand in Romanian re the Romanian Fable. (Box 118)
- Bill of Rights in the matter of impaneling of a grand jury. (Box 118)
- Material re Maude Hall vs. Imperial Water Company. (Box 119)
- Material re Ida Lub. (Box 119)
- Sample legal forms. (Box 119)
- Miscellaneous legal papers. (Box 119)
- Addenda
  - Judge Yankwich's book: It's libel or contempt if you print it... Part Two, Chapters 7-15., (Typescript draft, 2 copies) (Box 120)
    With holograph notes.
    [See also Box 13]
  - Judge Yankwich's book: The Nature of our Freedom., (Typescript draft) (Box 120)
    [See also Box 55]
  - Written opinions filed by Judge Yankwich as a Judge of the Superior Court with indication of the issue of the Journal or News in which they were published, August 10, 1927-January 1, 1932.; (Typescript drafts, vol.1-3) (Box 121)
    With index [incomplete].
  - Written opinions filed by Judge Yankwich as a Judge of the Superior Court, January 1, 1932-ca. 1935.; (Typescript drafts, vol.4-6) (Box 122)
    With indication of the issue of the Journal or News in which they were published.
  - re-election campaign., 1934; (Printed literature) (Box 123)
    Together with photostat copies of newspaper items covering the illegitimate parents epigram given by Judge Yankwich in Zipkin vs. Mozon, June 1928.
    [see also Box 28]
  - Printed bound volumes with index of appeals from cases tried by Judge Léon R. Yankwich., (vol.1-3) (Box 123)
  - Bibliography of Léon R. Yankwich, J.D., LL.D. Chief United States District Judge Southern District of California Los Angeles, California. (Box 124, Folder 1)
    See also below, Addenda.
  - Biographical Sketch for Who's Who (Léon René Yankwich). (Box 124, Folder 1)
  - Citizenship Ruling (Extension of Remarks of Honorable Cecil R. King of California in the Congressional Record of, June 27, 1955. (Box 124, Folder 1)
  - For Whom the Constitution? (Extension of Remarks of Honorable Cecil R. King of California in the Congressional Record of )., May 17, 1955 (Box 124, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between Judge James H. Pope, Judge of the Municipal Court, Los Angeles Judicial District, and Judge Yankwich (Separately indexed in detail for each year:, 1955-1957, and 1959). (Box 124, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1955; (Typescript leaves) (Box 124, Folder 2)
      - Transmittal letter for Its Libel or Contempt If you Print It, The Nature of Our Freedom, and a biographical sketch, August 8, 1955. (Box 124, Folder 2)
        Also refers to People vs. Nathanson, 134 ACA 52, and to printing of personal stationery and cards.
      - Reference to scrapbooks, titles and protocol of federal judges, April 12, 1955. (Box 124, Folder 2)
      - Transmittal for Talmud pamphlet, April 7, 1955. (Box 124, Folder 2)
        Also refers to son as Assistant Professor of Chemistry at University of Illinois and to son's research project financed by the Atomic Energy Commission (he is in the field of nuclear chemistry) and to his son's educational accomplishments at Berkeley
      - Judge Pope's letter re scrapbooks, Jewish Law and request to borrow copy of the Talmud article, April 11, 1955. (Box 124, Folder 2)
        Refers to papers of a juror consisting of warranties of slaves and letters regarding dispositions and punishment of slaves, and to sister's preservation of Pope family letters, etc., and to father's being a circuit rider of the Methodist Church in Ohio; Chief Justice Warren's history of the anti-segregation issue and the unanimity of the Supreme Court's decision though the deep South is represented on the court.
    - Correspondence, 1956; (4 typescript leaves) (Box 124, Folder 2)
      - Transmittal letter for paper on Unfair Competition as an Aid to Equity, May 16, 1956. (Box 124, Folder 2)
        Refers to The Art of Being A Judge lecture.
      - Transmittal letter for cards giving chief publications, etc., February 29, 1956. (Box 124, Folder 2)
      - Reference to Copeland Case and to individualization of punishment being legislatively destroyed through lack of understanding of the indeterminate sentence, February 20, 1956. (Box 124, Folder 2)
        Refers also to the enclosing of two articles (not by name).
    - Correspondence, 1957; (5 typescript leaves)
      - Judge Pope's thank you for copy of Individualization of Punishment in the Federal Courts, December 22, 1957. (Box 124, Folder 2)
        Refers to lawyers' reaction to value of collection of Judge Yankwich's writings.
      - Refers to appreciation of loan of Cornelius Cole papers and indexing of materials and impending retirement, December 16, 1957. (Box 124, Folder 2)
      - Refers to material and scrapbooks to be given to Judge Pope, December 13, 1957. (Box 124, Folder 2)
        Mentions: position of retired federal judge, the keeping of litigation background materials, basement storage of career materials (including the Snively Case), and the state of Ben Lindsey's unavailable materials.
    - 1959 Correspondence, (6 typescript and 1 photostat leaves) (Box 124, Folder 2)
      - Transmittal for (1) five scrapbooks 1927-35; (2) Manuscript of opinions rendered as a Superior Court Judge; (3) three bound books with index of appeals from cases tried showing wide range of problems, May 20, 1959. (Box 124, Folder 2)
        This letter mentions 70th birthday gift of three printed volumes containing the published opinions from the Pacific Reporter and the Federal Reports, and encloses a photostat of the preface written by Earl Warren, Chief Justice of the United States.
      - Judge Pope's letter acknowledging receipt of the letter of May 20 together with the three parcels of records for the Historical Collection of the County Law Library; and forwarding a copy of Guide to Special Collections by UCLA (1958) and requesting its return, July 27, 1959. (Box 124, Folder 2)
      - Requests that collection be consolidated at UCLA and describes the UCLA offer to catalog, etc., August 3, 1959. (Box 124, Folder 2)
  - Articles in Federal Rules Decisions (2 lists of 22). (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Charge to Grand Jury (Reprinted from Federal Rules Decisions, )., October 1954 (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Independence in the Judiciary (Extension of Remarks of Honorable Cecil R. King of California in the Congressional Record of ); What Kind of Independence Do We Ask in the Judiciary?, June 7, 1955 (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Magazine Articles (List of 33 with publication data). (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Magazine Articles (List of 47 with publication data). (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Narcotics and the Federal Law (Reprinted from The Georgetown Law Journal (vol.43, no.1), )., November 1954 (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Parody and Burlesque in the Law of Copyright (Reprinted from The Canadian Bar Review for )., December 1955 (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Individualization of Punishment in the Federal Courts (Reprinted from 20 Federal Rules Decisions, )., August 1957 (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - An American Judge Looks at the Talmud (an address delivered before the Western Jewish Institute at Los Angeles, California )., January 14, 1936 (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Unfair Competition as an Aid to Equity in Patent, Copyright and Trade-Mark Cases. (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Reprints [12] of articles published, 1951-1959. (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Individualization of Punishment in the Federal Courts, Address delivered at the Inservice Training Institute..., Claremont Men's College, August 6, 1956.; (13 leaves, ozalid, 2 copies) (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - Appellate Department Decisions of Judge L.R. Yankwich., (192 leaves, typescript [carbon copy]) (Box 124, Folder 3)
  - [Continuation of U.S. District Correspondence Files, (?)], 1935-1949
    [Continuation of the files contained in boxes 69-77]
    - M. (Box 125)
    - N - P. (Box 126)
    - P. (Box 127)
    - R. (Box 128)
- Material relating to the Campaign of, 1928.; (1 folder) (Box 129)
- Addenda no.2
  - Reprints of articles written by Judge Yankwich beginning A. (Box 130, Box 131, Box 132, Box 133, Box 134, Box 135, Box 136, Box 137, Box 138)
    - A - H. (Box 130, Box 131, Box 132)
    - I - O. (Box 133, Box 134, Box 135)
    - P - Z. (Box 136, Box 137, Box 138)
  - Manuscripts of articles written by Judge Yankwich. (Box 139, Box 140, Box 141, Box 142)
  - U.S. Court of Appeals assignments (Box 143, Box 144, Box 145, Box 146)
    - A.B.L. Brewing vs. C.T.R. to DeGarter vs. F.T.C. (Box 143)
    - Eisinger vs. Commissioner to Feil and Loeb vs. F.T.C. (Box 144)
    - Gamewell Company vs. Phoenix, Arizona to NLRB vs. Jones Lumber. (Box 145)
    - NLRB vs. Mountain Pacific, etc. to R.A.U. vs. C.I.R. (Box 146)
    - Sidebotham vs. Katz to Wong vs. Sweir. (Box 147)
  - U.S. District Court decisions. (Box 148)
  - Newspaper articles and miscellaneous papers, 1929-1966. (Box 149, Box 150, Box 151, Box 152, Box 153, Box 154, Box 155, Box 156, Box 157)
  - Law-Mirror of Civilization, I Established Law and Justice, Libel Trials - I. (Box 158)
  - Libel Trials - II, some famous trials. (Box 159)
  - Some famous trials, recordings, U.S. vs. Hunt. (Box 160)
  - Its Libel or Contempt.... (Box 161)
  - Court Correspondence. (Box 162, Box 163, Box 164, Box 165, Box 166, Box 167, Box 168, Box 169, Box 170, Box 171)
  - General Correspondence, A - K. (Box 172, Box 173, Box 174, Box 175)
  - General Correspondence, L - Z. (Box 176, Box 177, Box 178, Box 179, Box 180)
  - Miscellaneous papers from 3-Judge Navajo-Hopi trial in Prescott, Arizona; miscellaneous papers on 3-Judge Alcohol Beverage Control case in San Diego. (Box 181, Box 182)
  - Original manuscripts of articles. (Box 183, Box 184, Box 185, Box 186, Box 187, Box 188)
- Additions, 1975
  - Personal legal matters. (Box 189)
  - Mrs. Yankwich's traffic ticket - correspondence, briefs. (Box 189)
  - Personal correspondence. (Box 189)
  - Miscellaneous legal matters. (Box 189)
  - Notes on pleading and procedure. (Box 190)
  - Copy of Federal courts, C.A. Wright. (Box 190)
  - Personal notes. (Box 190)
  - Lecture notes. (Box 190)
  - Bankruptcy - citations. (Box 191)
  - Citations: A - I. (Box 191)
  - Citations: J - Z. (Box 191)
  - Notes on common law pleading. (Box 191)
  - Court rules and rules of practice. (Box 191)
  - Citations - his own cases[?]. (Box 191)
  - Biographical material. (Box 192)
  - Letters of recommendation, July 1935. (Box 192)
  - Letters urging Yankwich's appointment. (Box 192)
  - Photos. (Box 192)
  - Duplicates of photos. (Box 192)
  - Printed material by Judge Yankwich. (Box 193)
  - Mats for newspaper photos. (Box 193)
  - Printed material about Judge Yankwich. (Box 193)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 193)
  - Datebooks. (Box 194)
  - Book reviews. (Box 194)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, not by or about Yankwich. (Box 194)
    [All of the above have been put into chronological order within files]
  - Lectures and writings by Yankwich. (Box 195)
  - Property - business, personal. (Box 195)
  - Printed materials, some by or about Yankwich. (Box 196)
    Includes Diary (1933), Opinion book, Book copywrights (by Yankwich), and Romanian newspapers.
  - Correspondence, 1950. (Box 197)
  - Judges' salaries - statistics. (Box 197)
  - Administrative Office of U.S. Courts - correspondence and statistics. (Box 197)
  - Patent decisions - transcripts, etc. (Box 197)
  - Various personal files of correspondence and records. (Box 198)
    Includes biographical sketch, Salary memos, Helen Yankwich, UCLA Library, Retirement, Circuit court and Judicial conference.
  - Income tax records, other business and tax records. (Box 199)
  - [Various] books and magazines. (Box 200, Box 201, Box 202, Box 203)
- Additions, (Oversize material
  (dd, May 1989)
  - Scrapbooks of Clippings
    - 1934-1935. (Box 204)
    - 1931-1933. (Box 205)
    - 1933-1934. (Box 206)
    - 1930-1931. (Box 207)
    - 1954-1959. (Box 208)
    - 1935-1936. (Box 209)
    - 1946-1949. (Box 210)
    - 1950-1953. (Box 211)
    - 1926-1931. (Box 212)
    - 1931-1933. (Box 213)
    - 1937-1939. (Box 214)
    - 1936-1937. (Box 215)
    - 1930. (Box 216)
    - 1934-1935. (Box 217)
    - 1933-1934. (Box 218)
    - 1934. (Box 219)
    - 1927-1930. (Box 220)
    - 1926-1929. (Box 221)
    - 1959-1964. (Box 222)
  - Elections
    - Voting results, by precinct, 1934. (Box 222)
  - Scrapbooks of Clippings
    - 1928. (Box 223)
    - 1909-1918. (Box 223)
    - 1928-1929. (Box 224)
    - 1927-1928. (Box 224)
    - 1930. (Box 225)
    - 1929. (Box 225)
    - 1927-1930. (Box 225)
    - 1935. (Box 226)
    - 1941-1945. (Box 227)
    - 1939-1941. (Box 228)
  - Memorabilia
    - Certificates, degrees, memberships, drawings, caricatures, portraits, etc. (Box 229)
      [Formerly oversize packages 1-4, see above]
  - Reference files. (Box 232)